اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ
Musa(موسى) was told by Allah, that your people have worship the calf.
So, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
فَرَجَعَ مُوسَىٰٓ إِلَىٰ قَوْمِهِۦ غَضْبَٰنَ أَسِفًا ۚ
Musa(موسى) went back to his people; angry and upset, and sorry.
He is so sad.
How could this happen in my absence; my people commit Shirk(شرك), and they worship another god besides Allah?
So angry and upset.
So he went there to meet his people.
What did Musa(موسى) do, as soon as he saw his people worshipping the calf?
He threw the tablets.
Allah has given to Musa(موسى); Al-Alwah(الالواح); the tablets; that had the Huda(هدى) of Allah in them; he had the Awamir(اوامر); the commandments of Allah.
When Musa(موسى) saw, Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) making Sujood(سجود) to the calf; he threw the tablets from his hand.
What would you do if you see somebody throwing the Qur'an?
Something that, it's unacceptable!
But Musa(موسى); when he saw this in front of his eyes, he was in a state of shock.
So those tablets fell from his hand.
Musa(موسى) already knew about it, didn't he?
He already knew about it, because Allah told him.
How come his reaction was different, when he saw it?
Because Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
ليس الخبر كالمعاينة
When you hear something, it's not like seeing it.
Hearing about something is different than seeing it.
When you see something, it's a completely different thing then; when you hear about it.
Musa(موسى) heard about it from Allah, but when he saw it;
it was something different and, he was in the state of shock; he threw the tablets from his hand.
And he said;
قَالَ يَٰقَوْمِ أَلَمْ يَعِدْكُمْ رَبُّكُمْ وَعْدًا حَسَنًا ۚ
Oh my people! Did not your Lord promise you a fair promise.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has promised you with victory;
Allah has promised you with the Holy Land;
Allah has promised you with Jannah(جنة);
Allah has promised you with Tamkeen(تَمْكِين); establishment on the earth, if you are believers.
How could you leave all of these promises and commit Shirk(شرك)?
أَلَمْ يَعِدْكُمْ رَبُّكُمْ وَعْدًا حَسَنًا ۚ
أَفَطَالَ عَلَيْكُمُ ٱلْعَهْدُ أَمْ أَرَدتُّمْ أَن يَحِلَّ عَلَيْكُمْ غَضَبٌ مِّن رَّبِّكُمْ فَأَخْلَفْتُم مَّوْعِدِى۝
Did then the promise seem too long in coming?
Do you feel that it's too long in coming, so you gave up?
Or did you desire that wrath should descend from your Lord on you, that you broke your promise to Me.
You have broken your promise to Me.
They said;
قَالُوا مَا أَخْلَفْنَا مَوْعِدَكَ بِمَلْكِنَا
They said; We did not break the promise of our own will.
It is not our own will.
They refuse to admit their guilt.
قَالُوا مَا أَخْلَفْنَا مَوْعِدَكَ بِمَلْكِنَا
They said; We broke not the promise to you of our own will.
وَلَٰكِنَّا حُمِّلْنَا أَوْزَارًا مِّن زِينَةِ الْقَوْمِ فَقَذَفْنَاهَا فَكَذَٰلِكَ أَلْقَى السَّامِرِيُّ۝
But we were made to carry the weight of the ornaments of the people of Firaun(فرعون);
then we cast them into the fire and that was, what As-Samiri(السَّامِرِيُّ) suggested.
فَأَخْرَجَ لَهُمْ عِجْلًا جَسَدًا لَّهُۥ خُوَارٌ
Then he took out of the fire for them; a statue of a calf, which seemed too low.
Let's analyze; what Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) said?
Musa(موسى) told them; You're broke your promise with me.
They said; No! We did not break our promise with our own will,
but we were carrying with us ornaments and this is the suggestion of As-Samiri(السَّامِرِيُّ).
There are two problems with this;
Number one; they had guilt in their hearts because of this gold.
Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر) says;
First of all, this gold is Halal(حلال) for them now,
because the people of Firaun(فرعون) are the enemies of Allah, and Allah destroy them.
And that Ghanaam(غَنَام) should go to them.
So the gold; they should take it.
They had guilt for carrying that gold with them, but they did not feel any guilt committing Shirk(شرك) against Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
So the scale of Taqwa(تقوى) is upside down.
Taqwa(تقوى) is very small things but no Taqwa(تقوى) in the major issues.
So Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) are feeling the guilt of carrying with them, the gold that belongs to the people of Egypt;
and they have no guilt whatsoever, when they are worshipping a calf besides Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
أَفَلَا يَرَوْنَ أَلَّا يَرْجِعُ إِلَيْهِمْ قَوْلًا وَلَا يَمْلِكُ لَهُمْ ضَرًّا وَلَا نَفْعًا۝
Did they not see that, it could not return them a word and that, it had no power either to harm them or to do them any good?
And Haroon عليه السلام; he advise them;
وَلَقَدْ قَالَ لَهُمْ هَٰرُونُ مِن قَبْلُ يَٰقَوْمِ إِنَّمَا فُتِنتُم بِهِۦ ۖ وَإِنَّ رَبَّكُمُ ٱلرَّحْمَٰنُ فَٱتَّبِعُونِى وَأَطِيععُوٓاْ أَمْرِى۝
And Haroon(هارون) indeed, had said to them beforehand;
Oh my people! You are being tried in this, and verily your Lord is Allah the Most Gracious, so follow me and obey my order.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
أَفَلَا يَرَوْنَ أَلَّا يَرْجِعُ إِلَيْهِمْ قَوْلًا وَلَا يَمْلِكُ لَهُمْ ضَرًّا وَلَا نَفْعًا۝
Did they not see, that it could not return them a word, and that it had no power either to harm them or to do them good?
Sayidina Haroon عليه السلام was appointed to be the leader over Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) in the absence of Musa(موسى).
وَلَقَدْ قَالَ لَهُمْ هَٰرُونُ مِن قَبْلُ يَٰقَوْمِ إِنَّمَا فُتِنتُم بِهِۦ ۖ
ووَإِنَّ رَبَّكُمُ ٱلرَّحْمَٰنُ فَٱتَّبِعُونِى وَأَطِيععُوٓاْ أَمْرِى۝
And Haroon(هارون) indeed, had said to his people beforehand;
Oh my people! You are being tried in this.
This is a Fitnah(فِتْنَه); it's a test from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
And verily, your Lord is Allah; the Most Gracious, so follow me and obey my order.
Haroon عليه السلام is telling them; Allah is your Lord, so obey me and follow my order.
I'm the Ameer(أمير), I'm the Khalifah(خليفه) on you.
Because Musa(موسى) told Haroon(هارون);
وَٱخْلُفْنِى فِى قَوْمِى
Be the successor or be the leader on the people in my absence.
So, he appointed Haroon(هارون), and Haroon(هارون) told the people; You have to obey me;
فَٱتَّبِعُونِى وَاتَّبِعُواْ أَمْرِى
But Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); they were already set in there stubbornness to worship the calf.
Subhan Allah(سُبْحان الله)! This calf was so attractive to them.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَأُشْرِبُواْ فِى قُلُوبِهِمُ ٱلْعِجْلَ
Their hearts absorbed it.
Even long after the residual of that Ijl(عِجل) is still in their hearts.
This is way after Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَأُشْرِبُواْ فِى قُلُوبِهِمُ ٱلْعِجْلَ بِكُفْرِهِمْ ۚ
They absorbed the love of the calf in their hearts because of their Kuffr(كفر).
And Allah-u-Aalam(اللَّهُ أَعْلمَ); were they loving the calf because of the sounds that was making Khuwar(خوار)
or was it because Al-Ijl(العِجل) was made out of gold?
They said, what was the response to Sayedina Haroon(سيدنا هارون)?
قَالُواْ لَن نَّبْرَحَ عَلَيْهِ عَٰكِفِينَ حَتَّىٰ يَرْجِعَ إِلَيْنَا مُوسَىٰ۝
We will not stop worshipping the calf until, Musa(موسى) comes back.
Do whatever you want! We're not gonna stop worshipping the calf.
Musa(موسى); when he came back and he saw what they were doing;
the first thing he did was; he threw the tablets from his hand.
وَأَلْقَى ٱلْأَلْوَاحَ فِي نُسْخَتِهَا هُدًى
He threw the tablets and in the tablets; was guidance.
And then he rushed towards his brother,
and he grabbed him with his beard in one hand and his head in the other hand, and started pulling him towards him.
And he told his brother;
قَالَ يَٰهَٰرُونُ مَا مَنَعَكَ إِذْ رَأَيْتَهُمْ ضَلُّوٓاْ۝ أَلَّا تَتَّبِعَنِ ۖ أَفَعَصَيْتَ أَمْرِى۝
Oh Haroon(هارون)! What prevented you when you saw them, going astray, that you followed me not?
Have you then disobeyed my order?
Musa(موسى) said; How come, you didn't come and tell me?
How come, you let this happen and you didn't come and convey this news to me?
Haroon(هارون) said;
قَالَ يَبْنَؤُمَّ لَا تَأْخُذْ بِلِحْيَتِى وَلَا بِرَأْسِىٓ ۖ
Oh son of my mother!
Son of my mother, it means; he's trying to bring up the blood relationship that is between them.
And the mother is the side of mercy.
So he's telling him; we're brothers;
يَبْنَؤُمّ
Oh my brother! Oh son of my mother!
لَا تَأْخُذْ بِلِحْيَتِى وَلَا بِرَأْسِىٓ ۖ
Oh son of my mother! Sees me not by my beard, nor by my head.
إِنِّى خَشِيتُ أَن تَقُولَ فَرَّقْتَ بَيْنَ بَنِىٓ إِسْرَٰٓءِيلَ وَلَمْ تَرْقُبْ قَوْلِى۝
Haroon(هارون) is giving the justification; why he didn't come and tell Musa(موسى) of what is happening?
He said;
Verily, I feared lest you should say; you have caused a division among the children of Israel(اسرائيل), and you have not respected my word.
Haroon(هارون) said that; I would have caused disunity.
Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); when Haroon(هارون) told them; not to worship the calf,
they threatened Haroon(هارون), they said; We're gonna kill you.
And Haroon(هارون) said that; in other Ayah(آية), he said;
قَالَ ٱبْنَ أُمَّ إِنَّ ٱلْقَوْمَ ٱسْتَضْعَفُونِى وَكَادُواْ يَقْتُلُونَنِى فَلَا تُشْمِتْ بِىَ ٱلْأَعْدَآءَ
He said; They saw me weak, and they were almost going to kill me.
So don't let the enemy rejoice over us.
Haroon(هارون) was saying; Don't let the enemies because, we have some enemies among these people.
Some of them are enemies.
Don't let them rejoice because of the dispute between me and you.
So, whenever we have a conflict; we should keep it private.
If there's a conflict between the husband and the wife; it should not go out of the bounce of the household unless, it is necessary.
So the problems should be private.
And even, when Allahسُبحانه وتعالى said; you bring outside the systems, who did Allah say;
حَكَمًا مِّنْ أَهْلِهِ وَحَكَمًا مِّنْ أَهْلِهَا
Bring a judge from her side of the family and a judge from your side of the family.
If that doesn't work, then you bring somebody from the community as a judge.
The same thing, when we have a dispute as a Muslim ummah(امة),
we should keep it contained, and we should not bring the enemy from outside to solve it.
And when Muawiyyah(معاويه) was having a dispute with Ali(على);
the Romans felt that, this is their opportunity to make a move.
So they started to arrange their army and the news reach to Muawiyyah(معاويه)
because, Muawiyyah(معاويه) is the one who was close to the Roman Empire in the Ash-Sham(ألشَّام).
So Muawiyyah(معاويه) sent a letter to the emperor of the Romans, he said;
لا يضرنك خلاف ما ابن عمى
Don't let the dispute between me and my cousin, cause you to be overconfident.
If you do not stop; I'm gonna send you an army that starts here and ends, where you are.
Muawiya(معاويه) is telling them clearly;
Don't think that this dispute between me and my cousin will cause us to open door of opportunity for you to come in.
Haroon(هارون) is telling his brother Musa(موسى);
فَلَا تُشْمِتْ بِىَ ٱلْأَعْدَآءَ
Don't let the enemies rejoice over this.
Haroon(هارون) said; They were about to kill me.
ٱسْتَضْعَفُونِى
They saw Haroon(هارون) as weak.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has given every one of these Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء); all of the qualities he needs for this specific purpose that they're gonna fulfill.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has given Musa(موسى) a very strong and powerful personality because
he's gonna be dealing with a very stubborn people; Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
So, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has given him a very strong personality, and a strong body, and a strong character, and a strong presence.
When Musa(موسى) was there, they weren't dare to do this thing that, they did in front of Haroon(هارون).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has given Haroon(هارون) the qualifications; he needs as a wazeer(وزير) and advisor for his brother.
He has given him the ability to speak.
أَفْصَحُ مِنِّي لِسَانًا
Musa(موسى) said; My brother Haroon(هارون) is more eloquent or more clear in his speech to be an assistance for his brother.
Haroon(هارون); when Musa(موسى) was absent, Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) were about to kill him.
So Haroon(هارون) had to calm things down, until his brother would come back.
If he tried to enforce the law and prevent them from worshipping the calf,
that would have caused a rift and a dispute between Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) and the problem could get out of control.
And we know that when you make; نهي عن المنكر
You wanna make sure that it will not cause a bigger Munkar(مُنكر).
When you're preventing evil; one of the rules of preventing evil is that, it should not cause a bigger evil.
So Haroon(هارون) is not approving the worshipping of the calf.
He told his people.
See, because he has to make bayyan(بيان).
He cannot be quiet and then say, this is Hikmah(حكمة); No!
He has to tell the people that this is wrong, and he told them that this is wrong.
إِنَّمَا إِلَٰهُكُمُ ٱلرَّحْمَٰنُ
Your Lord is Allah; Al-Rahman(الرحمان).
But he waited until, his brother came back and then, he would leave it in the hands of his brother; Musa(موسى).
Musa(موسى) accepted that apology and he accepted the justification of Sayedina Haroon(سيدنا هارون).
So Musa(موسى) said;
قَالَ رَبِّ اغْفِرْ لِي وَلِأَخِي وَأَدْخِلْنَا فِي رَحْمَتِكَ ۖ وَأَنتَ أَرْحَمُ الرَّاحِمِينَ۝
Musa(موسى) said; Oh Allah! Forgive me and my brother, and include us both in your mercy, because you are the Most Merciful.
Musa(موسى) had a very soft and merciful heart.
Even though, he was in a moment of anger;
he was very angry and he was grabbing his brother by his beard and by his head.
But immediately, when he saw that his brother was on the right side, he started making Dua(دُعَا) for him and his brother.
And this shows the love of following the truth.
It is not stubbornness.
We don't follow our desires; we follow the Haqq(حَقّ) wherever it is.
So Musa(موسى) in the beginning, he saw that this was a mistake, so he came to stop it.
And then when the explanation was given to him,
he knew that his brother was doing the right thing, so he immediately made Dua(دُعَا) for his brother.
And then Musa(موسى) turned towards As-Samiri(السَّامِرِيُّ); the cause of all of this problem.
He said;
قَالَ فَمَا خَطْبُكَ يَا سَامِرِيُّ۝
And what is the matter with you; Oh Samiri(سَّامِرِيُّ)?
Musa(موسى); when he first came, Who did he first blame?
First; he directed the blame to his people.
And then who did he blame next?
Haroon(هارون)!
Finally, he blamed As-Samiri(السَّامِرِيُّ).
Even though, As-Samiri(السَّامِرِيُّ) was the cause of the problem.
Look at the Hikmah(حكمة) in that.
Who is the one who's responsible for this sin; it is the whole people,
because see, As-Samiri(السَّامِرِيُّ); if he gave this advice and that people didn't follow it; it wouldn't have occurred.
Always in every ummah(امة) they are going to be some people who will call to evil.
Now, is the ummah(امة) going to follow them or not?
So who carries the burden?
It is the ummah(امة).
It is the whole ummah(امة) of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
So Musa(موسى) directed the blame to them first.
أَخْلَفْتُم مَّوْعِدِى۝
He said;
أَفَطَالَ عَلَيْكُمُ ٱلْعَهْدُ أَمْ أَرَدتُّمْ أَن يَحِلَّ عَلَيْكُمْ غَضَبٌ مِّن رَّبِّكُمْ فَأَخْلَفْتُم مَّوْعِدِى۝
Do you want the anger of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى to come on you.
So he first blame the ummah(امة) of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
Because if they did not follow the advice; this problem would have stopped right there, and it wouldn't have occurred.
So in the beginning, it's the responsibility of the ummah(امة).
Any problem that we are going through today; it is our problem; the problem of the ummah(امة).
The problem that is happening in Iraq(عراق) or in Chechnya or in Kashmir(كشمير) or in Falastine(فلسطين) or in As-Somal(اسومال) or in Eritrea or any part of the Muslim world or in Sudan.
It is our problem collectively as an ummah(امة).
And then who does the blame go to next?
The leaders!
Musa(موسى) did not go and talk to As-Samiri(السَّامِرِيُّ) next,
he went to the Ameer(أمير); he went to the leader; he went to his brother; Haroon(هارون).
قَالَ يَٰهَٰرُونُ مَا مَنَعَكَ إِذْ رَأَيْتَهُمْ ضَلُّوٓاْ۝ أَلَّا تَتَّبِعَنِ ۖ أَفَعَصَيْتَ أَمْرِى۝
How come he didn't convey this message to me?
You are the leader, you are held responsible, you are held accountable.
And then in the end, Musa(موسى) went to As-Samiri(السَّامِرِيُّ) and told him; what's wrong with you As-Samiri(السَّامِرِيُّ)?
Because As-Samiri(السَّامِرِيُّ); he's following Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ), and he's only one person.
If the people and the leader stand against him; he couldn't do anything.
قَالَ فَمَا خَطْبُكَ يَا سَامِرِيُّ۝
And what is the matter with you; Oh Samiri(سَّامِرِيُّ)?
فَقَبَضْتُ قَبْضَةً مِّنْ أَثَرِ ٱلرَّسُولِ فَنَبَذْتُهَا وَكَذَٰلِكَ سَوَّلَتْ لِى نَفْسِى۝
I saw what they saw not, so I took a hand full of dust from the hoof print of the messenger; Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل), and I threw it into the fire.
Thus my inner self suggested to me.
And we talked about how he did this.
When Allahسُبحانه وتعالى was drowning Firaun(فرعون) and his army; Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) was there.
As-Samiri(السَّامِرِيُّ) was able; through an Ayah(آية); sign of Allah; something supernatural; was able to see Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل),
and was able to see the footsteps of Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) or the horse of Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل).
And he was picking up from that dirt.
And then he mixed it with the gold, which the woman of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) had;
and that gold belong to who?
To the woman of Egypt.
They mixed it together and they made the calf.
That calf started making some strange sounds like, a sound of a calf.
So they started worshipping it.
Musa(موسى) made his decision in terms of the punishment to As-Samiri(السَّامِرِيُّ);
he handed down the punishment to As-Samiri(السَّامِرِيُّ).
And that is that, As-Samiri(السَّامِرِيُّ) be exiled for the rest of his life.
Because of this sin, you cannot be part of our ummah(امة) anymore.
You have to leave us alone and we will leave you alone.
Musa(موسى) here is saying;
قَالَ فَاذْهَبْ فَإِنَّ لَكَ فِي الْحَيَاةِ أَن تَقُولَ لَا مِسَاسَ ۖ
Musa(موسى) said;
Then go away, and verily your punishment in this life will be, that you will say touch me not; you have a promise that will not fail.
قَالَ فَاذْهَبْ فَإِنَّ لَكَ فِي الْحَيَاةِ أَن تَقُولَ لَا مِسَاسَ ۖ وَإِنَّ لَكَ مَوْعِدًا لَّن تُخْلَفَهُ ۖ
Musa(موسى); In other word is saying;
Go! In this Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) you will not be with us, and we will not touch you.
And then he said;
إِنَّ لَكَ مَوْعِدًا لَّن تُخْلَفَهُ ۖ
We're gonna leave you now, alone; This is a punishment in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا)
and then in Akhirah(آخرة); there's another punishment that will be on you from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
And then he said;
وَانظُرْ إِلَىٰ إِلَٰهِكَ الَّذِي ظَلْتَ عَلَيْهِ عَاكِفًا ۖ
لَّنُحَرِّقَنَّهُ ثُمَّ لَنَنسِفَنَّهُ فِي الْيَمِّ نَسْفًا۝
Musa(موسى) said;
And look at your God to which you have been devoted; we will certainly burn it and scatter its particles in the sea.
He didn't even want to make use of the gold in it.
He said; we're gonna burn it all, and throw it in the sea.
And then Musa(موسى) said;
إِنَّمَآ إِلَٰهُكُمُ ٱللَّهُ ٱلَّذِى لَآ إِلَٰهَ إِلَّا هُوَ ۚ وَسِعَ كُلَّ شَىْءٍ عِلْمًا۝
Your God is only Allah; He has full knowledge of all things.
It is only Allah;
لَآ إِلَٰهَ إِلَّا هُوَ ۚ
None has the right to be worshipped but He;
He has full knowledge of all things.
They asked Allahسُبحانه وتعالى for Tobah(توبة).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى said; I will accept your Tobah(توبة), but there, there is a condition.
This crime is a very grave crime; it's a very big crime.
Therefore, the Tobah(توبة) for it; you have to sacrifice.
وَإِذْ قَالَ مُوسَىٰ لِقَوْمِهِۦ يَٰقَوْمِ إِنَّكُمْ ظَلَمْتُمْ أَنفُسَكُم بِٱتِّخَاذِكُمُ ٱلْعِجْلَ فَتُوبُوٓاْ إِلَىٰ بَارِئِكُمْ
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
And remember! When Musa(موسى) said to his people; Oh my people! Verily, you have wronged yourselves by worshipping the calf.
So turn in repentance to your Creator.
And what is the repentance?
فَٱقْتُلُوٓاْ أَنفُسَكُمْ
Kill yourselves!
This is a big sin; worshiping the calf is a big sin.
Therefore, they have to pay a price for the Tobah(توبة).
Because Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) kept on changing their mind, every now and then, they commit a crime
and then they say; Oh Allah! forgive us; they commit a crime; Oh Allah! forgive us.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى wants them to pay a price, and sacrifice; if they want their Tobah(توبة) to be accepted.
فَٱقْتُلُوٓاْ أَنفُسَكُمْ
Allah says in Qur'an; Kill yourselves!
What does this mean?
The Mufassireen(مفسرين) say, it means
that the ones who did not participate in worshipping the calf; kill the ones who worshipped the calf.
Even if, it is their father or their brother or their son.
And that's why, it's killing yourselves because; you could be killing your father or killing your son or killing your brother's like, killing your own self.
So all of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) had to pay a price even though, not all of them worshipped the calf.
But this happened in front of their eyes and they did not stop it.
So the Tobah(توبة) was; You kill yourselves.
So they took the knives and the swords and they started killing each other and it was a massacre.
It is said; in one day 70,000 were killed.
It was a massacre, blood was flowing.
This was their Tobah(توبة).
Because of the big sin they have committed.
They had to pay a hefty price for this Tobah(توبة).
وإِذْ قَالَ مُوسَىٰ لِقَوْمِهِۦ يَٰقَوْمِ إِنَّكُمْ ظَلَمْتُمْ أَنفُسَكُم بِٱتِّخَاذِكُمُ ٱلْعِجْلَ فَتُوبُوٓاْ اْ إِلَىٰ بَارِئِكُمْ
فَتُوبُوٓاْ اْ إِلَىٰ بَارِئِكُمْ فَٱقْتُلُوٓاْ أَنفُسَكُمْ ذَٰلِكُمْ خَيْرٌ لَّكُمْ عِندَ بَارِئِكُمْ فَتَابَ عَلَيْكُمْ
ۚإِنَّهُۥ هُوَ ٱلتَّوَّابُ ٱلرَّحِيمُ۝
Allah says;
And remember! When Musa(موسى) said to his people; Oh my people!
Verily, you have wronged yourselves by worshipping the calf so turn in repentance to your Creator and kill yourselves,
that will be better for you with your Creator.
Then He accepted your repentance.
Allah accepted it from them even though, it was Riddah(ردَّة); truly, he is the one who accepts repentance, the Most Merciful.
Musa(موسى) chose 70 men from the elders of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); the most prominent among them; the leaders of the people,
and he took them to the mountain; At-Toor(الطور), to meet with Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
Some of the Mufassireen(مفسرين) say; they went on that mission to apologize to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى for what Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) have done.
So this is a delegation from Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); going to apologize for what Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) have done.
وَاخْتَارَ مُوسَىٰ قَوْمَهُ سَبْعِينَ رَجُلًا لِّمِيقَاتِنَا ۖ
And Musa(موسى) chose out of his people 70 of the best men for our appointed time and place of meeting.
So they went to meet with Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
As I said; some of the Mufassireen(مفسرين)say; they want to apologize for what Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) have done.
When they got there, Musa(موسى) went into a cloud; the mountain was covered in a cloud.
They stayed outside.
Musa(موسى) went into the cloud, and they saw the light in which Musa(موسى) was standing in.
And Musa(موسى) was speaking to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
And then, Musa(موسى) came out.
When Musa(موسى) came out, these men; the best of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل), they said;
وَإِذْ قُلْتُمْ يَٰمُوسَىٰ لَن نُّؤْمِنَ لَكَ حَتَّىٰ نَرَى ٱللَّهَ جَهْرَةً فَأأَخَذَتْكُمُ ٱلصَّٰعِقَةُ وَأَنتُمْ تَنظُرُونَ۝
Oh Musa(موسى)! We are not gonna believe in Allah until, we see Him with our own eyes.
You come to apologize for the sin and now, you're putting these prerequisites.
لَن نُّؤْمِنَ لَكَ حَتَّىٰ نَرَى ٱللَّهَ جَهْرَةً
We're not gonna believe in your message until, we see Allah with our own eyes.
فَأَخَذَتْهُمُ ٱلرَّجْفَةُ
So the Earth shook, and they all fell dead.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَإِذْ قُلْتُمْ يَٰمُوسَىٰ لَن نُّؤْمِنَ لَكَ حَتَّىٰ نَرَى ٱللَّهَ جَهْرَةً فَأَخَذَتْكُمُ ٱلصَّٰعِقَةُ وَأَنتُمْ تَنظُرُونَ۝
But you were seized with a thunderbolt while, you were looking.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى sent on them; As-Sa'iqa(اَلصَّٰعِقَةُ); a thunderbolt; it killed them all.
Allahu Akbar(الله اكبر)!
Now, Musa(موسى) is in a dilemma.
Musa(موسى) took these 70, which are the best of the Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) to go and to apologize to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
These 70 are dead.
What will Musa(موسى) tell the people when he goes back?
The people will completely lose hope.
If these are the best of us and this is, what happened to them; We have no hope.
So Musa(موسى) knew that his people are going to be in; Halat-e-Ya's(حالتِ يأس); despair.
These are the best among us, these are the ones whom we expect Allah to accept their apology.
If Allah did not accept their apology, and Allah killed them all, what will happen to us?
Musaعليه السلام said;
فَلَمَّا أَخَذَتْهُمُ الرَّجْفَةُ قَالَ رَبِّ لَوْ شِئْتَ أَهْلَكْتَهُم مِّن قَبْلُ وَإِيَّايَ ۖ
Oh Allah! If it had been your will, you could have destroyed them, and me before.
Allah! If you wanted, you could have destroyed us before.
أَتُهْلِكُنَا بِمَا فَعَلَ السُّفَهَاءُ مِنَّا ۖ
Would you destroy us for the deeds of the foolish ones among us?
There are some among us, who are foolish; Are you going to destroy us all because of them.
إِنْ هِيَ إِلَّا فِتْنَتُكَ تُضِلُّ بِهَا مَن تَشَاءُ وَتَهْدِي مَن تَشَاءُ ۖ
أَنتَ وَلِيُّنَا فَاغْفِرْ لَنَا وَارْحَمْنَا ۖ وَأَنتَ خَيْرُ الْغَافِرِينَ۝
It is only your trial by which you lead astray whom You will, and You keep guided whom You will; You are our protector.
So, forgive us and have mercy on us; You are the best of those who forgive.
And then he said;
وَاكْتُبْ لَنَا فِي هَٰذِهِ الدُّنْيَا حَسَنَةً وَفِي الْآخِرَةِ إِنَّا هُدْنَا إِلَيْكَ ۚ
And ordained for us good in this world and in the hereafter, certainly we have turned on to You.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى said;
قَالَ عَذَابِي أُصِيبُ بِهِ مَنْ أَشَاءُ ۖ
My punishment I afflict there with whom I will.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى can punish whomever, He wills.
وَرَحْمَتِي وَسِعَتْ كُلَّ شَيْءٍ ۚ
And My mercy embraces all things.
The mercy of Allah embraces all things.
فَسَأَكْتُبُهَا لِلَّذِينَ يَتَّقُونَ وَيُؤْتُونَ الزَّكَاةَ وَالَّذِينَ هُم بِآيَاتِنَا يُؤْمِنُونَ۝
That mercy; I shall ordain for those who are Muttaqi(مُتَّقى); righteous, and give Zakah(زكوة),
and the ones who believe in our Ayaat(آيات), who are they?
الَّذِينَ يَتَّبِعُونَ الرَّسُولَ النَّبِيَّ الْأُمِّيَّ الَّذِي يَجِدُونَهُ مَكْتُوبًا عِندَهُمْ فِي التَّوْرَاةِ وَالْإِنجِيلِ
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
Those who follow the messenger; the prophet who can neither read nor write, whom they find written with them in the Taurat(تورات) and the Injeel(انجيل).
The Bisharah(بشارة); the glad tidings of Syedina Muhammadﷺ was given to Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) in that moment.
Where is it?
They hid it; they changed it; they altered it.
But the promise of Rasool Allah ﷺ was given to Musa(موسى) and this honour was given to Rasool Allah ﷺ in that time,
in the presence of the leaders of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
ثُمَّ بَعَثْنَاكُم مِّن بَعْدِ مَوْتِكُمْ لَعَلَّكُمْ تَشْكُرُونَ۝
Then We raised you up after your death so that, you may be grateful.
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى raised them up after their death.
Musa(موسى); he brought them; the laws of Allah, and he said; Follow them.
This is the law of Allah; you have to follow it; Give me your promise that, you will follow it.
Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) said; No! show us what is in there first, and then we're gonna tell you, are we gonna follow it or not.
This is coming from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى, and they know that it is the word of Allah.
They told Musa(موسى); we're not gonna follow it until, you let us know what is written there.
Show us what is there first.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَإِذْ أَخَذْنَا مِيثَٰقَكُمْ وَرَفَعْنَا فَوْقَكُمُ ٱلطُّورَ
And remember, when We took your covenant, and We raised above you the mountain.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى lifted up a mountain in the air,
and this mountain flew over Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل), and is stopped right there, like a cloud over their heads.
And then, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل);
You either follow the word of Allah otherwise, this mountain will crush you.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَإِذْ نَتَقْنَا ٱلْجَبَلَ فَوْقَهُمْ كَأَنَّهُۥ ظُلَّةٌ وَظَنُّوٓاْ أَنَّهُۥ وَاقِعٌۢ بِهِمْ خُذُواْ مَآ ءَاتَيْنَٰكُم بِقُوَّةٍۢ
خُذُواْ مَآ ءَاتَيْنَٰكُم بِقُوَّةٍۢ وَٱذْكُكُرُواْ مَا فِيهِ لَعَلَّكُمْ تَتَّقُونَ۝
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; And We raised the mountain above your heads as, if it is a canopy.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told them; You either follow the word of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى otherwise, you will be crushed under this mountain.
And Mufassireen(مفسرين) say; that Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); as soon as they saw the mountain above their heads,
they said; We're gonna follow, fine; we agree.
And they made Sujood(سجود).
Ibn Abbas(إبن عباس) says;
They didn't make the Sujood(سجود) on their forehead and on their nose;
they made Sujood(سجود) on their cheeks so that they can look with one eye up to the mountain.
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is giving Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) many chances.
An incident happened where, one old man from Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) was killed.
This man was wealthy.
They couldn't find out who killed him.
They didn't know; they tried; they searched.
Nobody admitted to the crime and they looked around; they didn't know who killed him.
So they went to Musa(موسى) and they said; Oh Musa(موسى)! We wanted to solve this crime.
Somebody is killed; We don't know who killed him; Solve it for us.
So Musa(موسى) asked Allahسُبحانه وتعالى for a solution to this problem.
Musa(موسى) went to Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) and said;
وَإِذْ قَالَ مُوسَىٰ لِقَوْمِهِۦٓ إِنَّ ٱللَّهَ يَأْمُرُكُمْ أَن تَذْبَحُواْ بَقَرَةً ۖ
Musa(موسى) went to his people and said; Allah is commanding you to sacrifice a cow.
They said; What are you making fun of us; Are you joking with us?
We're asking you to solve a crime of somebody who was killed, and you're telling us to kill a cow.
What are you talking about?
They said;
وَإِذْ قَالَ مُوسَىٰ لِقَوْمِهِۦٓ إِنَّ ٱللَّهَ يَأْمُرُكُمْ أَن تَذْبَحُواْ بَقَرَةً ۖ قَالُوٓاْ أَتَتَّخِذُنَا هُزُوًا ۖ
They said; Do you make fun of us?
What did Musa(موسى) say?
إِنَّ ٱللَّهَ يَأْمُرُكُمْ
Allah is commending you.
And Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) said; that you making fun of us, are you joking?
Look at the rude; rudeness of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
What do you mean, Musa(موسى) is joking with the name of Allah?
Musa(موسى) will tell you; go and sacrifice a cow, Allah is telling you to sacrifice a cow, and you go and tell him;
you're joking, Are you making fun of us?
This is not appropriate for a righteous man to do, let alone a Nabi(نَبِي) of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; a prophet; to use the name of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى in jokes.
But this is; it shows you the manners and the Aadab(آداب) of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
قَالُوٓاْ أَتَتَّخِذُنَا هُزُوًا ۖ قَالَ أَعُوذُ بِٱللَّهِ أَنْ أَكُونَ مِنَ ٱلْجَٰهِلِينَ۝
I seek refuge in Allah from being an ignorant or a foolish.
I'm not making fun of you; this is serious.
Allah told them; sacrifice a cow.
Now, if you would follow that order, what does it mean?
You go and take any cow.
But, Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) asked too many questions.
So they went to Musa(موسى) and said;
قالُوا ادْعُ لَنا رَبَّكَ يُبَيِّنْ لَنا مَا هِيَ
They said; Call upon your Lord for us, that He may make plain to us what it is.
So they asked a question, they're gonna get an answer.
قالَ إِنَّهُ يَقُولُ إِنَّها بَقَرَةٌ لَا فارِضٌ وَلا بِكْرٌ عَوانٌ بَيْنَ ذلِكَ فَافْعَلُوا مَا تُؤْمَرُونَ۝
Verily, it is a cow neither too old nor too young but, it is between the two conditions; so do, what you are commanded.
So now, their pool of choices narrower.
It has to be middle aged cow, it can't be old; it can't be young.
So they went and they looked at the cows.
And then they came back to Musa(موسى) and said;
قالُوا ادْعُ لَنا رَبَّكَ يُبَيِّنْ لَنا مَا لَوْنُها
Oh Musa(موسى)! Can you ask Allah to tell us what colour it is?
قالَ إِنَّهُ يَقُولُ إِنَّها بَقَرَةٌ صَفْراءُ فاقِعٌ لَوْنُها تَسُرُّ النَّاظِرِينَ۝
It is a yellow cow, bright in its colour pleasing the beholders.
Now, it has to be yellow; and yellow is rare, and it has to be pleasing; when you see it, you're pleased.
So now, they're even forced to go into a smaller choice.
Now, the choice is becoming narrower and narrower; the pool of choosing is smaller.
They went and looked around at the cows and then they came back.
قالُوا ادْعُ لَنا رَبَّكَ يُبَيِّنْ لَنا مَا هِيَ إِنَّ الْبَقَرَ تَشابَهَ عَلَيْنا وَإِنَّا إِنْ شاءَ اللَّهُ لَمُهْتَدُونَ۝
They said; Call upon your Lord for us to make plain to us, what it is; to make plain to us, what it is.
And then they said; Verily, to us all cows are alike.
We went and we saw, all the cows; they look the same.
إِنَّ الْبَقَرَ تَشابَهَ عَلَيْنا
All these cows, they look the same to us.
If they look the same; go and take one of them and sacrifice it.
Why do you have to ask all these questions?
They felt that they are asking too many questions.
They knew that, so they said;
وَإِنَّا إِنْ شاءَ اللَّهُ لَمُهْتَدُونَ۝
They said; And In Sha Allah(إنْ شاءالله); we'll find the right one.
قالَ إِنَّهُ يَقُولُ إِنَّها بَقَرَةٌ لَا ذَلُولٌ تُثِيرُ الْأَرْضَ وَلا تَسْقِي الْحَرْثَ مُسَلَّمَةٌ لَا شِيَةَ فِيها
He; Musa(موسى) said;
It is a cow neither trained to till the soil, nor water the fields, sound, having no other color except bright yellow.
So this cow now does not till the Soil, nor water the fields, it is sound, it has no problems with it.
So, these are additional descriptions which are narrowing their choice.
They went around and they found only one cow that fulfills these conditions; only one.
In all of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); only one cow, and it is said that, this cow was owned by an orphan.
Somehow, the orphan knew that Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) want this cow badly.
So he made business out of it.
He knew that there's no cow that has these qualities except this one.
Not only tripling the price.
He said; If you want this cow, you have to pay me its weight in gold.
You have to pay me its weight in gold.
He knows how to make money out of a cow.
And Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) were forced to pay its weight in gold because, that was the only cow that fulfills the conditions.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
قالُوا الْآنَ جِئْتَ بِالْحَقِّ
When they saw this cow, they said; Now, you have brought us with the truth.
They told Musa(موسى); now, you have brought us with the truth.
As if, he was joking or lying to them before it; it shows you, how rude they were with their Nabi(نَبِي).
فَذَبَحُوها وَما كادُوا يَفْعَلُونَ۝
So they slaughtered it.
Though, they were near not to do it; they barely did it.
Why did Allah tell them to slaughter a cow?
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى wants to perform an Ayah(آية); miracle in front of their eyes.
وَإِذْ قَتَلْتُمْ نَفْسًا فَادَّارَأْتُمْ فِيهَا ۖ وَاللَّهُ مُخْرِجٌ مَّا كُنتُمْ تَكْتُمُونَ۝
And remember; when you killed a man and fell into dispute among yourselves, as to the crime.
But Allah brought forth that, which you were hiding.
فَقُلْنَا ٱضْرِبُوهُ بِبَعْضِهَا ۚ
So, we said; Strike him; the dead man with a piece of the cow.
Take a piece of that cow which is dead, and strike the dead man with it.
You gonna have life.
So the dead man who was killed; when they touched him with the dead flesh of the cow; the man stood up alive,
and he started to speak, and he said; My nephew is the one who killed me.
Because he killed him for the inheritance.
My nephew is the one who killed me and then, he died again.
It was a miracle of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى. Allah says;
كَذَٰلِكَ يُحْىِ ٱللَّهُ ٱلْمَوْتَىٰ وَيُرِيكُمْ ءَايَٰتِهِۦ لَعَلَّكُمْ تَعْقِللُونَ۝
Thus Allah brings the dead to life, and shows you His Ayaat(آيات); His signs so that, you may understand.
But Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
ثُمَّ قَسَتْ قُلُوبُكُم
Then, after that; your hearts were hardened, and they are as hard as rocks are even harder.
Subhan Allah(سُبْحان الله)! A heart can be harder than rocks.
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; There are some rocks;
وَإِنَّ مِنَ الْحِجَارَةِ لَمَا يَتَفَجَّرُ مِنْهُ الْأَنْهَارُ ۚ
And indeed, there are stones out of which rivers gush forth.
And there are stones where water flows from them.
And there are stones that fall down for fear of Allah.
And your hearts are even worse than stones.
There are stones that can produce water;
there are stones where rivers can come out;
there are stones that would fall down from the Khash'ya(خَشْية) of Allah;
and your hearts are stone; they're producing nothing; they have no Khash'ya(خَشْية) and no fear of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
This lesson of Al-Baqarah(البقرة); a few comments on it.
It is not appropriate to come to the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) of Allah, and ask them too many questions,
that don't have a good purpose behind them or that are not beneficial.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told the people in Sahih Muslim(صحيح مسلم); this Hadith(حديث) is narrated by Muslim;
أَيُّهَا النَّاسُ قَدْ فَرَضَ اللَّهُ عَلَيْكُمْ الْحَجَّ فَحُجُّوا
Rasool Allah ﷺ said; Oh people! Allah has made it mandatory on you to make Hajj(حَجْ); so make Hajj(حَجْ).
One of the men present, it's a clear order from Rasool Allah ﷺ; make Hajj(حَجْ); very clear; doesn't need any explanation.
One man stood up and said; Every year?
أَكَلَّ عَامٍ
Should we make Hajj(حَجْ) every year?
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not answer.
The man stood again and said;
أَكَلَّ عَامٍ
Should we make Hajj(حَجْ) every year?
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not answer.
He stood up a third time and said; Shall we make Hajj(حَجْ); he's insisting.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
لَوْ قُلْتُ نَعَمْ لَوَجَبَتْ وَلَمَا اسْتَطَعْتُمْ
If I said yes, it would have become mandatory on you, and you would not be able to do it.
Why are you asking the question?
If I said yes, there it would become mandatory on you to make Hajj(حَجْ) every year, and you will not be able to do it.
Why are you bringing difficulty on yourselves?
And then, Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
ثم قال : ذروني ما تركتكم فإنما هلك من كان قبلكم بكثرة سؤالهم واختلافهم على أنبيائهم ،
فإذا أمرتكم بشيء فأتوا منه ما استطعتم ، وإذا نهيتكم عن شيء فدعوه
And then, Rasool Allah ﷺ said; Leave me alone, with what I have left you with.
What has destroyed the people before you; is because of there going back and forth to their Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء), and asking them questions.
If I tell you to do something; do the best you can, and if I prevent you from doing something; don't do it.
Don't ask too many questions.
If I tell you to do something; do as much as you can.
Because the orders of Islam are many, and many of them are recommended.
We can't do them all .
So Rasool Allah ﷺ knew that, and he said;
فأتوا منه ما استطعتم
Do as much as you can.
But in the things that are Haram(حرام); you don't do them, period.
فإذا نهيتكم عن شيء فاجتنبوه
If I tell you; not to do something; that Don't do it.
Don't ask too many questions, and this is to the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء).
Now, this needs to be understood in the right way, does not mean, that you worship Allah on ignorance.
If you don't know something, then you need to ask.
Because, we have a situation which is mentioned in Hadith(حديث); Abi Daud(أبى داؤد);
عن جابر قال: خرجنا في سَفَر فأصاب رجُلا مِنَّا حَجَرٌ فَشَجَّهُ في رأسه، ثم احتلم
Jabir(جابر) says; We were travelling, and there was a man with us who got injured with a stone.
A stone came in his head; rock came and knocked him in his head, and it injured him.
And then he had a wet dream at night.
So when he woke up, he was in Janabah(جنابة), when he woke up in the morning.
He said;
فقال: هل تجدون لي رُخْصَة في التَّيمم؟
Do you find any excuse for me to make Tayammum(تَيَمُّم); is it allowed for me to make Tayammum(تَيَمُّم)?
فقالوا: ما نَجِد لك رُخْصَة
We don't find any excuse for you.
You have to make Ghusl(غُسل).
He said; Can I make Tayammum(تَيَمُّم).
They said; No! you have to make Ghusl(غُسل).
They gave him a Fatwa(فتوى).
وأنت تَقْدِرُ على الماء
And you are able to touch water;
فاغْتَسَل فمات،
He took a shower, and he died.
They told him; We don't find an excuse for you, you have to bath; you're not able to make Tayammum(تَيَمُّم).
So, the news was carried to Rasool Allah ﷺ;
فقال صلى الله عليه وسلم: قال قَتَلُوه قَتَلَهُم الله
ألا سَألُوا إذ لم يعلموا
فإنَّما شِفَاء العِيِّ السؤال،
إنما كان يَكفيه أن يَتيمَّم ويَعْصِب على جُرحِه خِرقَة،
ثم يمسح عليها، ويَغسل سائر جسده
Rasool Allah ﷺ said; They killed him; may Allah kill them.
They killed him! Why do they ask, if they do not know?
Because the cure of ignorance is asking.
How come they didn't ask?
They did not know, why did they give him a Fatwa(فتوى); and they don't know?
They should ask.
شِفَاء العِيِّ السؤال،
The cure of ignorance is asking.
It is enough for him to make Tayammum(تَيَمُّم), and tie a cloth on his head, and then wash the rest of his body.
But the water; when it hit the injury, it killed him.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ is saying here; that you need to ask.
And also we learned something important from this Hadith(حديث); Don't give Fatwa(فتوى) if you don't know.
Wallah(والله)! I have brothers coming, and telling me about things that they are told. Unbelievable!
People are giving Fatwa(فتوى) right and left.
May Allah forgive us all, we all make mistakes, all of us, we make mistakes.
But sometimes, there are some of us, and whenever a question is presented, they have an answer.
They have an answer for everything.
They know it all.
Everything, they can answer.
You could answer a question, and you could cause the death of somebody like this.
The Shariah(شريعة) is not a game that you play with.
When you don't know say; Allah-u-Aalam(اللَّهُ أَعْلمَ).
Somebody travelled from Al-Maghrib(المغرب) or from Andalus; from the extreme west to Al-Imam Maalik(الاِمَام مالِك) in Madinah(مَدِينَه).
He had 40 questions.
He asked Al-Imam Maalik(الاِمَام مالِك), these 40 questions; Al-Imam Maalik(الاِمَام مالِك) answered 34 of them with;
لا اعلم
I don't know;
34 questions out of the 40; 34 he said, I do not know Allah knows best.
The man said; I came all the way from Morocco to hear that you don't know.
Al-Imam Maalik(الاِمَام مالِك) said; I don't know.
This man travelled all the way.
And now, sometimes, we volunteer; we jump into a conversation and we volunteer an answer.
لا اعلم نصف العلم
Some of the Ulama(عُلَمَا) said; I don't know is half of knowledge.
A sign of knowledge is, when you say I don't know; that shows that this person has some knowledge.
They came to Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) once,
and we learned two things from this Hadith(حديث) of this incident to the Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب).
Somebody asked Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) a question when Umar(عُمَر) was a Khalifah(خليفه).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said; Did this thing happened?
هل وقعت
The man said; No.
He said; Okay; go back home; when it happens; then come back and ask me, and I will gather the people of Badr(بدر) to give you an answer.
We learned from this Hadith(حديث) of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) that,
we should not try to know about things that we don't need to know about.
If the incident did not happen, why hypothesize?
I mean; there are some outrageous things like, this question that was presented to the Fuqaha(فُقَها).
This is in the old time; this question was presented to the Fuqaha(فُقَها).
They said; What if somebody is carrying wind in the bag?
You know, wind? It comes out from the body.
They said; Somebody gathered that wind in a bag,
and then he put it on his back, and then he flew in the air.
They did not have airplanes in the time.
And then he flew in the air.
Can he pray with that wind on his back?
Look at; this is somebody who has nothing to do, and is laying down on his bed, thinking about these hypothetical situations.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said; I'm not gonna answer the question.
If it did not happen; I'm not gonna answer it.
Go back home, when it happens, then come back;
and what did Umar(عُمَر) say? He said; I'm not gonna answer it.
جماعت لک أهل البدر
I'm gonna bring the people of Badr(بدر), who are still alive; and make a council; and then we're going to give you a Fatwa(فتوى).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) cannot give a Fatwa(فتوى) alone.
He has to bring the people of Badr(بدر) to give a Fatwa(فتوى); Allahu Akbar(الله اكبر)!
Now, in the time of the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء); they were not supposed to ask some questions because, Wahi(وحى) was still coming down.
Now, you need to ask questions if you don't know.
If you don't know something; ask question. But ask questions about;
العلم الذي ينفع
Ask questions about knowledge that will benefit you. Don't ask about;
علم لا ينفع
Don't ask about knowledge that will not benefit you.
And Rasool Ullah is also saying in the Hadith(حديث);
اللَّهُمَّ إِنِّي أَسْأَلُكَ عِلْمًا نَافِعًا، وَأَنعُوذُ بِكَ مِنْ عِلْمٍ لاَ يَنْفَعُ
I asked You to give me knowledge that will benefit me; and I seek refuge in You from knowledge that does not benefit.
Subhan Allah(سُبْحان الله)! If you look at the method of Qur'an; the methodology of Qur'an;
you find that Qur'an does not mention dates; did not mention places.
I mean, there is no historical record in Qur'an, You don't find any dates mentioned whatsoever.
Why?
Because, the dates of when things happen; don't have anything to do with the Hidayah(هداية).
This book; Qur'an; is a book of guidance; So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى put the Huda(هدى) in it.
But when you compare it to the Bible; you find that everything in the Bible has dates,
and numbers, and places, and it has the family, the name of the family members of every person that has mentioned in there,
and who they got married to, and their life story.
If you're looking in Qur'an; you find that Qur'an has not even mentioned the stories of the birth of the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
It did not give the dates of their birth; it did not even mention the stories of the births of the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) with the exception of Eesa(عيسى).
Why?
Because of the importance of the birth of Eesa(عيسى) in guidance.
Because Eesa(عيسى) was worshipped besides Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
Why?
Because of his miraculous birth.
They said that; He is the Son of God.
That's why, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى talked about the birth of Eesa(عيسى) in Qur'an.
But Allah did not talk about the birth of Muhammadﷺ;
He did not talk about the birth of Saleh(صالح); or Hud(هود); or Ibrahim عليه السّلام; or Nuh(نوح); Allah did not talk about their births.
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى just mentioned; the Bisharah(بِشَارَه); the glide tidings of the birth of Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل), and Is'haq(إسحاق);
because of the miracle in it; because it was to an old man; Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) and an old woman; Sarah(ساره).
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى also talked about the birth of Sayidina Yahya(سيدنا يحيى).
Because of the miracle in it too;
Zakariyya(زَكَرِيا) was old in age, and his wife was old in age.
And a lot after about the creation of Adam(آدَم); which is his birth.
But Allahسُبحانه وتعالى did not talk about the birth of anyone else.
Musa(موسى); Allah talked about the birth of Musa(موسى), because of the miracle; the Ayah(آية) in his birth.
At least, the early parts of his life; there is a miracle in it.
So, we need to concentrate on the knowledge that will benefit; and we should look at the fruits of knowledge.
They came to the Imam Ahmad-Bin-Hanbal(اِمَام اَحْمَدْ بِنْ حنبَلْ) and, they said;
I think they were talking about Bishr al hafi(بشرالحافى) or one of the Ulama(عُلَمَا).
They came to Imam Ahmad-Bin-Hanbal(اِمَام اَحْمَدْ بِنْ حنْبَلْ) and said; He's not a scholar.
Why?
Because he doesn't know a lot of Fiqh(فقه), and he does know a lot of Hadith(حديث).
They said; He's not a scholar.
Imam Ahmad-Bin-Hanbal(اِمَام اَحْمَدْ بِنْ حنْبَلْ) said; He already has the fruit of knowledge.
And that is;
خَشْيَةِ اللهِ عَزَّوجَلْ
The fear of Allah.
You're saying; He doesn't have knowledge, he already has the fruit of knowledge.
And what is the fruit of knowledge?
The fear of Allah.
إِنَّما يَخْشَى اللَّهَ مِنْ عِبادِهِ الْعُلَماءُ
The ones who fear Allah are the scholars.
Now, this man fears Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; so he has the fruit of knowledge.
So we should seek the fruits of knowledge.
And we should study the knowledge that benefits; the knowledge of Huda(هدى); guidance.
And get away from the details, and the minor issues, and the disputable issues, that add nothing or subtract.
And Subhan Allah(سُبْحان الله)! Sometimes, we have big disputes about things,
that are not gonna put you in Jannah(جنة) or put you in hellfire; if you do them or you don't.
Some very, very minor issues, when Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has told us that our unity is a priority.
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّم